So, the great thing about slot props is that it's very explicit.
You can see here that you're defining the prop here, and then when you're accessing
the slot prop here, it actually tells you what it is.
And then for those of us that don't like to have a bunch of prefixes, you can actually
destructure it, so it actually can just look like this as well.
That's a standard JavaScript, nothing of you, that's just normal JavaScript.
Okay, so you're probably thinking, okay, this is cool, but there's got to be some
cons to this, right?
And there is.
What is called scope slot is because the context in which you're exposing the
data is within a very specific scope.
What does that scope?
The slot.
Meaning, we cannot now just go, hey, I want to do like constable count here, and then
be like return count dot, like that's not possible.
This prop is only exposed at the slot level, and so essentially, you're really only
doing it for like, in my most of the time you're just doing it for
display purposes and rearranging things.
You're not trying to combine the logic and honestly, I'm not sure you would want to do
that, you get really messy if you're able to do that.
That's something to consider as far as how you can do that.
Now, the other technique that I want to introduce you to is something called use slots.
Why is use slots helpful?
Let's say, for the footer, as you would expect, you have like an actual footer element
that wraps this, and let's just say it has a bunch of my custom footer classes on it.
And let's go ahead and actually eliminate any default content, because, well, sometimes
sometimes there's no content.
The problem with this is you might be able to imagine, is that when this is rendered,
the footer element is still going to, the footer DOM element is still going to be rendered.
Meaning you have essentially like orphaned HTML elements that really shouldn't be there
up to begin with.
And so what you can do is, if we import use slots, which is a helper method, it basically
exposes what slots are being used inside of a given component at any time, like what's
being passed in.
So we can see here, use slots.
And so what we can do is you can see here, I can go VIF slots dot footer.
That should do the trick, and if we come over to the demo, oh, I have something in here.
We can inspect.
And if we take a look, that VIF has removed the footer element as you would want.
And so this gives you additional control over how you want to actually use your slots,
because before knowing this, your initial temptation might have been to just wrap everything
in like a template block.
And so you might have done something like this, and so you might have done like slot
name is footer, and then you would have like thrown this inside of like thrown your
footer element inside.
But again, this only like, well, I mean, frankly, you're providing the slot content to
render.
So you kind of, it's not really what you can easily get out of it.
And so this is why it's just a very clean way to basically check like, hey, does my slots
contain like a footer slot, and so this is related to this name, by the way, that's
what these two are connected.
And so yeah, it's just a great way for you to programmatically get access to it.
And then do any logic that you need to accordingly based on whatever slots are available
to you.
So as far as design patterns go, you'll notice that we focus a lot on composition in a lot
techniques we talked about.
In other words, like most of us when we start out with you, we learned about props,
we learned about emits, and those are what we consider more configuration type design
patterns.
Very explicit about what API you're going to be using.
I'm using this, and this, and I'm going to use it this way.
But the problem with that is that it's very rigid, right?
And so you can imagine, especially with there's an exercise that I do in the production
great view course, where you take a base button and you add all these requirements to it.
And if you do it, the props way, your props become a walking dictionary.
And it's very, very difficult to navigate.
It's one to if icon is left, then show this, and then if icon is right, show that it's
pretty miserable.
But composition, and I think one of the reasons why composition API has also taken
off the way it has is because it allows you to really organically grow your components
to a point where it does make sense to specialize them, whereas configuration, you specialize
immediately.
You're like, oh, I want a button that has a left icon, then you create a prop that says
left icon equals this.
Instead of like, here's a button, you can put stuff in it, use it.
And then if over time you're like, oh, I noticed fifth, like 500 components have always
used a left button icon with these styles.
Then that's when it makes sense to be like, okay, we're going to create a base button,
let's say left icon.
And then that can refactor all that out.
And then so what you get is what I like to do about data driven refactoring, rather than
sort of like when you're doing props is easy to get into like optimizing what you think
you might eventually need, composition kind of frees you of that, because you can totally
expand to whatever you need, but at the same time you're not bound to those very rigid
definitions upfront.
So just something about is not that you should never do configuration.
In fact, we saw in some of our base text base components that when you're certain
things are, you absolutely want to be in their configuration is really helpful.
But composition is the one I do try to get with the default to when they're designing
their components is a more flexible and just easier to evolve.
Would the most common use for scope slots be the past components into them, light a career
rearrange components that way?
Yeah, you could.
Yeah, yeah.
So because with the scope slot, I mean, you have free reign of like whatever you want
that data to be used.
And I mentioned this, I guess I didn't demo this early, but you can technically feed
methods into it too, so functions.
And so if you're like rearranging a modal, for example, and you know that it has a closed
functionality already in your child, it doesn't necessarily make sense to like create something
that like throws it to the parent.
So through a scope slot, you could theoretically expose that method to that one section, call
it like an action slot.
And then in the action slot, you just create whatever button or arrow you want, and then
just call like the child's closed method.